We've been exploring context engineering
and a range of orchestration tools
designed to create thorough plans for AI
agents to follow. But the big problem is
is that you still need to provide exact
context for each specific task.
Otherwise, the agent starts filling in
the gaps on its own, often drifting away
from the original plan and building
something completely different from what
you intended. But I think I've just
found a tool that actually solves this
and it's called Tracer. The most
advanced AI coding assistant built for
large code bases. Tracer starts every
task with a detailed actionable plan.
This means you can iterate with AI on
ideas, not cryptic code diffs. You can
update the plan with precision and
tracer ensures the plan artifact stays
coherent and fully grounded to your
actual codebase. Think of it as a
planning layer. It makes sure the input
going into the agent is crystal clear,
leaving no gaps that can cause
hallucination. Tracer even has its own
intelligent thinking process to detect
loopholes and works with you to resolve
them before coding begins. And what's
even better is that you can spin up
multiple planners in the background that
allows you to get more done faster. And
when the AI agent encounters something
new like an unfamiliar UI library or a
framework, Tracer automatically gathers
the context it needs to implement it
properly. So to get started, you can
easily install it through Visual Studio
Code and it works with all of the
different agents that we showcase from
Cloud Code, Cursor, Rue Code, and many
others. But you can simply install it as
an extension within your IDE. So in my
case, I'm using Visual Studio Code and I
can head over to the extension tab and I
can search up Tracer and I can simply
install it. And after installing, you're
going to be requested to create an
account with Tracer. So simply go ahead
and do that and then we can get started.
After signing up or logging in, you're
going to be then greeted with this
extension page. But before I even get to
that, I simply just had an AI model
generate a resume AI application where
it generated the base structure of the
SAS landing page with the capabilities
to use AI to enhance your resume. Now,
this is a very basic app, but I have one
requirement and that was to give the AI
model to use MUI. It failed to
incorporate all of these components that
I had requested it to generate within my
resume AI app. And the reason why is
because most AI assistants handle
popular libraries like Shad CN really
well because they're actually trained on
them. Uh now what I'm going to do is
actually showcase how you can use Tracer
AI in this case a bit further and see
how it can handle something like
incorporating a pretty complex task of
handling something like a new library
like MUI which most models actually tend
to fail at doing due to it being really
new and its inability to actually
process new context. So now heading back
into the tracer agent, we can actually
use it to help us implement this new
context to our actual app. In this case,
I can describe my prompt, the task as
descriptively as possible in natural
language. And this is where I'm telling
it to integrate the MUI library and
replace certain components a part of my
resume app. You can then tag certain
components that you want to work with.
You can even upload different images as
well. But there's two different modes
that you can use. One is the phases
mode. This is where you can start a
conversation with the AI and it's going
to essentially clarify the intent of
your task and then break it down into
tasks that are manageable. Then you also
have the plan mode. This is where you
can get a detailed file level plan,
refine it with AI, and then send it to
the agent for execution. But what I want
to do is work with the AI to actually
build up a manageable task to implement
the MUI library. So we can go ahead and
send this in. This is where the AI agent
is going to now converse with me to
implement new steps to actually work on
this task. It'll use reasoning to map
out all the different files that you
have and then it'll thoroughly
understand the structure and then work
on an implementation plan that you can
actually help the AI develop.
So it looks like it has returned with
the response and it said that it found
that my project is a vanilla HTML CSS
JavaScript app and it's not a React
project. So it has given me a couple
options where I can first go ahead and
have it work on converting it to React
plus MUI which is the recommended one.
But you also have a couple of other
options like using material design CSS
framework or a hybrid approach. But I'm
going to be using option one. So let's
go ahead and send that in. And like we
had talked about this phases mode is
where it's going to be able to break it
down into manageable steps. And you can
see right here that it has created a
thorough plan as to how it will tackle
it. So you can see the first one is to
set up the React project structure and
the dependencies where you can go ahead
and first generate the plan. This is
where it's going to start mapping out an
implementation plan for that specific
phase breakdown. In the same manner, it
will do the same for all of these other
phases, which is where it's going to
thoroughly help us implement this MUI
library. So, it looks like the first
phase has been fully planned out as to
how it would create the React app. And
now what you can do is you can actually
execute it with whatever agent that you
want. You have it so that you can
execute it with co-pilot, pod code or
even tracer. And you can even configure
more AI agents to tackle this particular
task. But you can even chat with the
plan. So if there's like certain areas
that you think would need work or you
would want to change a plan, you can
definitely talk to the AI and change a
plan that it has actually devised and
it'll make that implementation. I
personally like it. So I just simply had
Tracer accept the changes. And now you
can see that it is developing and
creating the new source directory for
the React app within my resume app. So
looks like tracer has finished executing
phase one. So now you can actually go
ahead and apply the changes. You can
even show the diff so that you can see
if everything was correctly done. Now
after accepting all the code changes,
you can simply just click apply all. And
then what you can also do is have tracer
verify and make sure that everything
that it had generated is thoroughly
correct. And what's cool is that after
it has finished verifying, it's going to
give you a couple of review comments
that you can then implement and fix with
the AI agent that you have configured.
But once you have it configured, you can
then reverify it to test if that
particular error has been resolved. But
you can see that with each particular
step, there is a detailed plan that will
make sure that this implementation
process is 100% correct and without any
sort of error. And you can obviously go
ahead and update certain components that
you don't like so that it saves you time
and the review process at the end. And
just take a look at the code changes. If
you want to get a full reference, you
can definitely see exactly which file is
new, which it'll thoroughly state. And
it will also state which file has been
modified. So this way it'll give you a
reasoning behind each change, each edit
as well as each creation. Now I have
thoroughly finished all the different
phase breakdowns that was generated
using Tracer. And there we go. We have
an implementation of the new Réé AI app
using the MUI component. And it looks a
lot cleaner and more modern. This best
fits a RSé app. And you can see
everything is still the same and even
focus on adding new components to the
overall app. You have an AI powered
resume builder built within that is a
bit more streamlined than what it looked
like before. You have a pricing tier,
frequently asked questions, and then you
also have it categorized using different
components that was provided using MUI.
And this is what I really wanted. It was
able to thoroughly generate while
keeping the main structure that we had
requested before. And it looks a lot
cleaner and a lot more professional
thanks to Tracer. If you like this video
and would love to support the channel,
you can consider donating to my channel
through the super thanks option below.
Or you can consider joining our private
Discord where you can access multiple
subscriptions to different AI tools for
free on a monthly basis plus daily AI
news and exclusive content plus a lot
more. This is the capability of Tracer
and this is why it is something that
stands out for planning far deeper than
many of the different kits that we have
showcased like spec kit. Yeah, BMAD,
even context engineering. It offers a
streamlined UX and one-click handoff to
your favorite AI agent so that you can
have it execute almost any complex task.
But that's basically it guys for today's
video on Tracer. If you're interested in
getting started, you can actually take a
look at the coupon, which is listed in
the description below, where if you want
to access the Tracer Pro account, which
is valued at $25 per user a month, it is
something that you can get access to for
only $1 for the first month using the
coupon code. So, if you're interested,
definitely take a look at it with the
links in the description below. But with
that thought, guys, thank you guys so
much for watching. I hope you enjoyed
today's video on Tracer. I'll leave all
these links in the description below.
Make sure you go ahead and subscribe to
the second channel, join the newsletter,
join our private Discord, follow me on
Twitter, as well as making sure that you
subscribe to the YouTube channel, turn
on notification bell, like this video,
and please take a look at our previous
videos because there's a lot of content
that you will truly benefit from. But
with that thought, guys, have an amazing
day, spread positivity, and I'll see you
guys fairly shortly. He suffers.